A lot of people online say
that you need to be using a teleprompter,
you need to be
writing down and scripting everything you
say, and if you don't, that you're not
going to be able to maximize your views
or your sales.
And I'm here today to tell you that's
bullshit.
[objects crashing] My name's James Smith,
and I do live
events,
sometimes in front of thousands of people,
sometimes in front of hundreds.
I do this social media thing,
and although you're on one of my niche
channels at
the moment, I have other big channels.
Over a million on Insta,
over a million on TikTok,
half a million on YouTube.
So we're going to talk a little bit about
how to present, how to speak, and
potentially how to do live events.
But better yet,
how to attract an audience without having
to script every
word that you have in a video.
You may have seen some of my other videos
before
where I critique people's social media
content.
And just quickly before we get into it,
if you want me to have a look at your
website,
have a look at the content you put out,
and give you some live critiques,
there's going to be a link in the
description.
You can click on that anytime for free.
You can see how long it's been since we've
used this from the amount of dust on it.
And quickly, to anyone watching
that doesn't know what this is, this is a
teleprompter. Every time you watch TV
and the people, "And today, welcome on the
show.
We've got a number one 'Sunday Times'
best-selling author," they're reading,
and there's a little script in front of
them.
They become heavily reliant on it, and
if you look carefully at their eyes,
you can
see their eyes reading the words.
What you don't know is almost every single
content creator, especially on YouTube,
sounds so smart because they're
reading words as they come up, and this
is a teleprompter.
Just before we get into the different
types of teleprompter that there are,
let's
look at the benefits of
when it would be a good idea to use one of
these.
If you are creating a course
or something that's got loads of nuance
and
there's something really deep
and complex you need to go into, actually,
you
probably do need a teleprompter,
because if you're going to be recording
for 30,
40, 50, 60 minutes, not only
are you going to experience lapse in
concentration,
courses are actually writing projects
that you bring to life by talking to
camera.
Now, another time
that I would say you should definitely get
a teleprompter is
doing something that I call the 50/50
test.
I work with loads of small businesses
trying to help them to grow online, and I
don't know whether
or not they're going to be better off with
a teleprompter or
without.
So I get them to spend 50% of the content
that they put out raw
dogging it, sticking it out, no lube,
without planning, and the other 50
meticulous planning out, strategizing,
creating a prompter flow that they can
read through. And of course,
this landscape has changed a lot in the
last two
years with ChatGPT,
because you can write an amazing video
plot, education style theme, whatever,
and you can just chuck it into Uncle
GPT and say, "Yeah.
Can you write this better?" And it
is only through doing some
videos with and some videos without
that you can go look at the performance of
those videos to see what people
were vibing with.
Because onto a quick side tangent,
which I probably wouldn't have thought
about if
I had scripted this video
is a lot of people seem to think with
social media, we're
trying to beat the algorithm.
But we're not.
We're trying to resonate with humans.
And if we can win with humans,
we're going to win on the algorithm.
And sometimes when people just raw dog it
and spit the bars from
the heart, people enjoy it more.
Feels less robotic.
So the only way you can know that
is to test.
Bit like trying to figure out
if your missus likes it in the arse.
Obviously,
you don't just stick your dick in the
arse. Come on.
But without putting a digit in there,
you're never going to know.
And they might not be sure,
because most men aren't even sure.
Where were we, Declan? Does it feel nice?
I don't know. It feels like I'm pooing.
Him or her? I don't know. Relax. Now,
sometimes there can be very complex
parts of a video,
so you might be free balling the entire
video, but then when it
comes down to breaking down the Krebs
cycle or the legal
implications or citing something
scholarly, or even
reading out part from a study,
that could be the perfect opportunity to
bring that
teleprompter in so you can, "In 1942,
there were 72 people that
conducted a randomized control trial using
rodents, and they found out that..."
Whatever. Anyway.
And the only other two possible places
that I would say it's good
to use a teleprompter is
when you may be brain dead.
So let's say you know you're on set all
day filming ads or doing
shoots or whenever I'm doing Nu Tonic
stuff with Chris Williamson.
And another time I would say potentially
is if you're doing
something live and in front of an
audience.
Now,
I have had the benefit of speaking in
front of some very big crowds, and
although you'll notice that
when your favorite comedians do a stand-up
TV show,
they will be reading from a teleprompter.
You can tell by the cadence of their
voice.
I sometimes think
that there's a perfect middle ground
between the two.
Did the light just go off? Continuation,
Declan. There you go.
Even this little technical error
that we've had here
is another reason why it's
okay to free ball. Continuation?
That's the word, isn't it?
If that light was to remain off-
Continuity. Continuity. That's the one.
That's why even moving the camera could be
terrible for us. Live talks.
Some people like to read teleprompters,
but there's actually something
that you can
look at in front of people next time you
go to a live show, and it's called a
comfort monitor. Whenever I present,
if you look carefully in front of me,
there's
three little screens on the stage,
and there's a clicker in my hand.
Now, for some talking points,
the clicker changes what's behind me.
If sometimes there's a visual
or something that I want to present,
it's up there.
But if there's really important talking
points that I want to have and make sure
that I don't forget,
I have them as click-through replicate
slides.
So let's say there's an image behind me
and I've got five talking points.
I will replicate
that image five times in the presentation,
and then each part,
there is an element in PowerPoint,
in presenter mode,
that will come up on your
comfort monitor. For instance,
on my last tour, I spoke about a
Soviet Lithuanian psychologist called
Bluma Zeigarnik.
That was interesting,
just in case I forgot her name.
I then spoke about something that
was called the Zeigarnik effect.
And when you're in front of 2,000 people,
sometimes you forget the word Zeigarnik.
Then I would click,
and the next slide would come up
and saying that waiters and
waitresses, she observed that there
was a phenomena that they remembered what
everyone ordered at the table up until the
point they paid.
Then when people paid,
the waitresses used to forget.
So she came to the conclusion
that pending tasks take up more cognitive
function than things that are put to bed.
It's why we create cliffhangers in films
or TV series.
Whenever there's some curiosity
and a loop is opened,
our brain remains very
active. But the second
that we close the loop,
our brain can relax, so to speak.
And that has now been called the Zeigarnik
effect.
So even though I'm joking
and maybe cracking jokes at one element of
the
talk,
when I get into something in the
nitty-gritty where I want to make sure I
don't forget anything,
having those click-through prompts in
front of me can help
me understand.
I even sometimes put in those little
slides, "James, tell
this joke." The Zeigarnik effect I utilize
to empower people to give them more
confidence. So for instance,
if you're on the train
and there's someone that you
think is really fit and you're single,
and you want to approach them
and give them
your number,
you could be penalized through not doing
it.
Because if you don't do it,
you'll be thinking about it all day,
all week, all
month. Next time you go on a date,
you might be sat in front of a person
that you
don't really fancy that much
and you're just thinking about the person
on the
train. However, if you
were to take action
and to potentially set the metrics of
success as asking the person,
not getting the number, which
is another video
altogether. Where in essence,
you could say, "I'm going to ask
that person for
their number. Even if they say no,
I've won." Whereas if you were to set your
success metric as,
"I'm going to talk to that person,
get their number, go on a
date,
and fall in love," the likeliness of there
being success in that scenario are
much, much less. See,
when we started planning this video,
I never thought we were
going to talk about the Zeigarnik effect,
yet here we are.
So planning and strategizing for a live
talk 100%
going to do it.
But I'm not going to write down every
single word, I'm just going
to put in the things that
are most important.
And just how we get into how you can put
that into your content, let's move into
the next part.
When not to use a teleprompter.
The first thing would be
if you're not very skilled at using a
teleprompter,
because reading from a teleprompter
is a skill in itself.
First of all,
you need to look at the cadence of the
words moving and compare that
to how quick you speak naturally.
You're then going to want to make sure
that your
lens size and how wide the text is,
how tall the text is, is all in the right
place,
so that your eyes aren't moving across the
screen like it is right now when
I'm going left to right,
pretending to read words.
Even little things.
It's very important that when you
are talking to camera, that you break eye
contact. Because this
is only a human thing.
If you sit opposite someone
and they just stare at you
and they never break eye
contact, it becomes very, you're, "Whoa,
mate. Hold on, mate.
Get out my face." So even
when I'm reading from a teleprompter,
occasionally I will
just break eye contact. Again, which
is part of the skill of doing it,
but you can
only do it getting better. So
if you're someone in the infancy of
wanting to put
out content and grow your audience,
and you could be three to six months away
from
being good at using a teleprompter,
you could be setting yourself up to go
backwards. And some people,
probably the third scenario I would say
is the worst,
is where people think
that using a teleprompter
is a replacement for
something I would call raw experience.
Nothing beats raw experience.
Let's look at driving.
First time you get in a car,
learn to drive.
I'm like, "Fucking hell, Dad, why
are there three pedals in the car? Go,
stop.
What's the third?" "Clutch." "What
is that, Dad?
Where's that been?" "Have you not seen
your mum changing gears over the years?"
I'm
like, this has all crept up on me.
And nothing beats getting better at
driving than
doing more driving.
You've got other scenarios.
Being in the workplace.
First few weeks of work,
you're absolute shit in it.
After a few months, normal.
Editing. First time you start editing,
you're like, "Oh, chop.
Oh, delete." Next thing,
you're like 'Minority Report,' moving
stuff about.
With content, it's the exact same.
The only reason that you may think I'm
good at content is I've done it
more than you. If you
were to watch me bowl in a bowling alley,
chances are
whoever's done it the most bowls the best.
Chances are darts.
Any skill. Any skill. The more you do it,
the better you get.
But don't think that you can
circumnavigate or take shortcuts using the
teleprompter, because it's unlikely.
Now, if you want to ignore my advice
and still use a teleprompter, I've got you
backed here.
Introducing the Elgato Prompter.
Good thing about this, USB-C,
plugs it into your computer.
It works as another monitor, let's say,
with a little reflection area here.
Second thing that's good
is you can get these little camera mounts.
So you can put that onto the lens at the
end of your camera.
Probably only going to work
if you're using a proper lens.
You're not going to get
that on the end of a shitty camera.
And it's not really going to work with
something like a DJI Pocket Osmo 3.
Now,
the benefit of this over a traditional
prompter is, let's say you're doing a
podcast and you want to look at your guest
in the
eyes.
You could drag your guest from their
screen and put them onto the monitor,
so that when you're looking at them,
they are there.
Some people will do a podcast,
their guest will be on a laptop to the
side, and
they're just going to stare at a camera
pretending they're looking at the guest.
For this, it's amazing.
Then another very kind of good type of
teleprompter is just a purely reflective
one.
And this bit here is where you put an
iPad.
So all of those prompters come with apps.
And with those apps,
you type out your file for whatever it is,
you paste it into
the app. They come with a little remote.
I can then stick an iPad in front, start,
stop, speed up, go back.
Most of my business mentorship courses
are done on the iPad one.
Now, of course,
when people become proficient at using
prompters, they
sound smarter. They sound smarter.
Even you could say not um-ing, uh-ing,
thinking.
The fact that you go from one point to the
next.
And I must admit,
although I do love free-balling videos,
sometimes planning a
little bit,
you can work at a slower speed.
This is why I much prefer using a Discord
with my business than I do doing live
calls with people.
Because sometimes you need to sit
and mull and think and then go
back a little bit
and give some more nuance.
And again,
probably the main benefit of one of those
would be if you are doing
something arduous or long-winded
or a long period of time or something
course related, having a teleprompter
or some planned strategic
notes for a live show alleviates stress.
So when I'm doing live events,
and I'm going back to back,
and I'm doing the
Hammersmith Apollo one night,
and then I'm going up to Manchester the
next.
If I'm super tired
and my brain isn't functioning at 100%,
I know that I'm not
going to miss anything because I've got
the prompts there ready, and I can click
through to them. Same like today.
I'm knackered today.
I went to the Lions the weekend in
Melbourne.
I got smashed two nights in a row.
Yet I'm here bossing this video because of
a little secret that I'll teach you
about in a sec. Now, the reason
that I'm not using a teleprompter right
now. The first one
is I actually really enjoy random tangents
that we
go on.
We've spoken about fingers in the
assholes, and potentially some other
comical things,
purely because I've been given the freedom
to talk about what I
want. I think because of that,
it can seem more genuine.
So although I do take you on little side
tangents and B stories and sometimes
can overshare.
A bit like the time I prematurely
ejaculated in Barcelona.
Long story short,
I've never been terrible at premature
ejaculation.
Have you, Declan? No, he gives me the nod.
However,
there was one time in Barcelona in my
early 20s where I was
invited around someone's house on a Sunday
morning, and I'm not sure
if the stars aligned. I'm not sure
if Pluto was out of its
sync with Neptune or whatever it was.
But for some reason,
I prematurely ejaculated,
and it must have been, I'm
talking sub 45 seconds. And imagine this,
if you will.
I was trying to convince someone
that I'd never met before that this
is the only
time I'd ever prematurely ejaculated.
So can you imagine that, Declan,
for a second, mate?
Met a girl, first time you met her.
Knowing me in my early 20s, I was probably
giving it big on Tinder.
Forty-five seconds in, whoopsie.
So then I'm trying to use all my energy to
try and convince this stranger that
this never usually happens before.
It's the first time it's ever happened.
And she's like, "Yeah." Because that
is exactly what someone who prematurely
ejaculated all the time would say.
And I sometimes think
that maybe in the upcoming
years from that,
she might have walked into WHSmith
and seen my book and gone,
"That's the guy that told me he could last
more than 45 seconds." So that
tangent right there would never in a
million years be in my notes, but it's
fun and it's jovial,
and it humanizes the whole thing,
because guess what?
If me and you were to go for a beer
together, that's the exact thing
that I talk
about, as Declan knows. So if we
are going to free-ball, and if we
are going to do
this style of video,
how can we ensure
that we get everything
that we need to into
a video?
It's time to introduce to you
that very one thing.
The Google Doc As you can see in front of
me, I've got the Google Doc.
Then all the things
that we've spoken about before are here.
I've actually already planned the title,
and the thumbnail, and the
introduction. And you'll notice
that here I've just got talking points,
just things
to talk about.
And then I've even said here to show
previous documents of other
videos. So if we go to docs.google.com,
I've got
courses that I've written, videos,
I've got emails, I've got
everything I could ever need.
And sometimes it's just a few notes.
I've even got a BDO expenses form here for
my accountants.
Anything I need,
I sometimes just make a little Google Doc
video.
And then I even put an idea here
that maybe as I was going to show you
this, I
was accidentally going to click
and I'd be watching a Joe Wicks workout.
I thought that could be quite funny.
I open my laptop and they're like, "Oh,
what's this?"
It's Joe Wicks.
But I feel like we've had enough banter.
Get back to it.
So why Google Doc?
It's easy to share with the editor,
because often Declan right
now is probably enjoying his last days of
being able to access porn without having
to upload a picture of his fucking
passport. Know about this in the UK?
Mate, UK now, you want to watch porn,
and we're traveling to the UK in a few
weeks,
you've got to upload a pic of your
passport, mate. You got a VPN?
Of course you have. You millennials
are all about frictionless wanks.
Me, I'm too old for a VPN.
So I can send this to Declan.
So even if he wasn't listening to anything
I spoke about this whole video, which
could be likely, I don't blame him,
he has to do this all the time.
He can look through the document
and see where he needs to do stuff.
Two,
if we're going to link to different videos
and resources, I can put them in
the doc and Declan can then go
and rip them from other websites, SnapTik,
IG Reel Downloader, whatever it is.
And I then have a menu of what to talk
about.
And then if something is too complex,
I could always just put it in.
And even better yet,
if I wanted to read a subsection of
something complex, I
can just read it like this,
and then Declan just could put overlay,
not only giving
the contextual reality of what's going on,
but then that means I can look
away from the camera for a while
and you're no the wiser.
Then if Declan's good, what's cool
is you can just tell your
editor how to edit.
So I've even said here, "Declan,
let's get a jump cut in
on the part of me saying how to edit." So
he's then going to chop that bit of text.
Then he's going to zoom in.
He will have to move a little bit to keep
my eye line
in the same place.
And then I can even say underneath,
"Now Declan,
show them telling me to tell you how to do
this," which is the section I've just
put,
because he might have thought to cut
that out. It's like inception. Moving on.
And then here I've just got my outro.
Planning is great.
As we can see here, it's almost integral.
But the issue is with over-planning
and over-preparation and scripting
videos from top to bottom,
we can create a level of quality of
content that's just
too high. And what that means
is you now say, for a video,
I need to plan.
For me, I need to plan, I need to write.
If I need to write,
I need to allocate an hour into Google
Doc, whatever.
Now suddenly it's an hour of work to even
start filming, which for me is just too
much. So many of our videos
that we've done,
especially some of the ones that
perform best on this channel,
we just point and shoot.
There was no planning at all. There
was nothing to it.
And I think that too many people online
aren't sharing that with you and saying,
"Hey, sometimes just hit record
and just go for it." Too many people
are like,
strategize, plan. For some, yes,
but for others, absolutely not.
Because I don't think enough creators
are talking about the fact that content
frequency is so important for so many
reasons, and it's
actually really good
that you do put out videos
that don't do well from time to
time, and you do put videos that do.
But not all of them should be perfect.
If all your videos are perfect,
I would say you're not posting often
enough,
because then you're not getting enough
feedback from things.
If you don't have a system in place where
you can produce fast and easy content,
then all of your content will be slow
and hard, and that is a problem.
For the people whose businesses
that I help,
I teach them to make 100 videos as
fast as possible,
which can seem like really boring business
advice.
But these are the reasons. First one,
something I coin the seven-hour rule.
I believe that people might need to spend
seven hours in front of you before
they're going to buy your shit,
whether you use YouTube, short form,
whatever it
is. It could even be podcasts.
Great way to get into that.
So if you're not putting out content
frequently enough,
that accumulation of that
time before they buy it,
it's just going to be too long.
You've got that outlier rule.
The majority of creators that I know,
their video
that was the outlier,
they never expected to be the one
that blew up.
And it's often sometimes a piece of
low-value content
that they didn't even know
was going to resonate that well. And
if they weren't in a groove of putting out
content so frequently,
it would never have happened.
Most people are surprised by the video
that explodes.
And also by focusing on 100 videos more
than focusing on making
amazing videos,
you can focus more on the process,
not the outcome, which is the
most important thing for everything.
You need to fall in love with every
component of this.
Then when you upload it to the internet,
that's the end.
Similar to what I said about asking the
girl or the boy for their number on the
tube,
you need to determine what success looks
like.
And for me,
I seek success as everything we're doing
now, recording, editing,
putting it out. Because
if I set success as the video performing
really well, and
it doesn't perform well, that's not a win.
Where instead,
we need to become wholly focused on the
process.
The creating the videos, the posting,
the talking to the person, asking them for
the number. The outcome will come
if you focus on the process.
But if you focus on the outcome,
you'll get deflated, you'll get depressed,
and you
will not make it through as a creator.
And the final lesson is this.
It's only in doing 100 videos as fast as
you can that you can see the
impact and benefits and progress
and experience that you can gain from
100 videos.
It's only through doing 100
that you know what 100 can do, which
gasses you up to do the next 100.
Whether that's with a teleprompter,
whether it's
free-balling,
you need to try everything as fast as you
can on a daily
basis. Now, like I said before,
there's a link in the description where
if you want
me to critique your content
and give you some honest feedback,
I'll do it for free.
But if you're someone
that just wants to make better short-form
content, I've
created a course.
We've had over 4,000 people go through
this course, and people
are loving it.
So those links will be in there.
Thank you very much for watching.
We might as well give them an end card,
eh, Declan? Let's have a look.
So now we're trying to strategize between
Declan, because this has been unplanned,
as to what video we should give you as an
end card.
So
let's go look at revenue, right?
It's got to be the laziest way to make
money
in 2025. It's done $12,000 in US revenue.
So now let's think of another hook.
So if you love the idea of not scripting
your videos because you're a bit like me,
a little bit lazy,
I've actually put together the laziest
ways that you can make
money in 2025,
and this video has compelled more people
to buy my
stuff than any other before. So be careful